My mother was the first person in town
我媽媽是這個鎮上
to die from the mold.
第一個死於黴病的
It grew inside her lungs,and multiplied,
它在肺部裏成長而且日漸茁壯
and made it difficult for her to breathe.
使她的呼吸變得困難
For a short while she acted strange I guess.
有一段時間她的行徑變得很怪異，我想
Later, the mold spread to her brain,
後來，黴擴散到他的大腦
and she died of a hemorrhage.
接著死於大量出血
But, we didn't know that at the time.
但，那時我們並不知道
At the time she was just dead.
她就這樣走了
At first,
起初，
the men in the white suits came from town.
穿著白套裝的男子從城鎮過來
They took samples, and did tests,
他們取了樣本，做了測試
and put everything into little plastic bags.
接著將所有東西裝入小塑膠袋裡
Later, they took the chair
最後，他們將母親的座椅
my mother died in to the dump
棄置在垃圾堆裡
for the trash trucks to pick up.
任由垃圾車接走
The man said it was infested.
男子說那是個寄生體
That the mold had found a home
在黑暗又潮濕的布料中
in the damp darkness of the fabric
黴病找到了歸屬
and then spread to the rest of the house...
接著散播至房裡的各個角落
We had to pack what was left of our stuff
我們必須收拾其餘的個人物品
and go live with my grandmother.
之後和祖母一起生活
But even that was a false kind of peace.
那也只是偽裝的平靜
The next day,
隔天
a girl from down the road died,
住在街尾的女孩去世了
and the night after that
再隔夜
the whole Lawson family
整個Lawson家族
passed away in their sleep.
在睡夢中死去
The ambulance, and the men in white suits
救護車和白套裝的男子
came again.
再度到來
They put more things in bags
將更多的物品裝進袋子裡
and marked off the houses with yellow tape.
用黃色膠帶為房子做記號
After that,
在那之後
it was all anybody could talk about.
就成為大家口中唯一的話題
At school,
學校裡
the teachers showed us slides, and pictures,
老師用幻燈片撥放了一些照片
and talked a lot about science,
並且說了許多關於科學研究的事
but it didn't seem like
但他們似乎也並
they understood it either.
不是完全很了解
It was a rare and deadly kind of mold
黴病是一種罕見且致命的病
and they weren't sure what caused it.
而他們其實也不確定是甚麼原因造成的
They told us about a case once in Russia,
老師告訴我們一個在俄羅斯的案例
where all these cows had died
那裡的牛全死了
like, thousands of cows,
上千隻
and then everybody in the town died too
接著整座城鎮的人們跟著死亡
because they didn't have enough to eat.
因為沒有足夠的食物能夠存活
Later,
後來
they figured it was
他們才發現
something growing in the grass.
有東西在草裡擴長
The preachers made a big deal of it,
傳教士們拿此大作文章
and everybody went to church
使得所有人
almost every day.
幾乎每一天都會去教堂
They were always praying
總是祈禱著
and singing and hugging each other.
唱歌以及互相擁抱
And outside of church,
然而在教堂外
there was a lot of talk of other stuff too
對此有另外的說法
If it was a curse of some kind,
說它其實是種詛咒
or a hex.
或蠱惑
A lot of people thought that
許多人認為這件事
was what had happened,
就是這樣發生的
and wondered who had brought it,
並揣測是誰引起
and what had they done?
還有他們做了些甚麼
Anyway, the mold came
總之，黴病侵入
and the mold stayed.
且停駐
The preachers couldn't pray it away,
傳教士門無法將它驅逐
and the scientists couldn't figure it out.
科學家們也無從解釋
They found it in kids backpacks,
黴病出現在小孩的背包上
and silverware drawers.
放餐具的抽屜裡
People were going around in masks
群眾到哪都載著口罩
like at the hospital all the time.
就像一直待在醫院一樣
They said it floated around in the air
人們說它懸浮在空氣裡
and that you could breathe it in.
你可能會將它呼吸至體內
The days and hours passed like
那些日子和時間裡
we were all underwater,
我們就像是被悶著
or just walking around
或就像是一直用
with cotton in our ears.
棉花將耳朵持續塞住
But, every time we would go to the dump,
但，當每次我們去垃圾場
there would be my mother's chair.
母親的座椅依然在那裏
The trash trucks would come and go,
垃圾車來了又去
and the chair would stay.
座椅仍在
It was my grandmother who first noticed this,
祖母是第一個注意到這件事的人
and later it became her obsession.
後來這件事就成了她的一種執念
That perhaps the chair had brought
她認為就是那座椅
all of this darkness and suffering,
帶來了所有的邪惡和苦難
and only the chair could take it away.
只有將座椅丟棄才能帶走這一切
It got to the point where
這就是為什麼
if the chair wasn't gone,
這張座椅並沒有被帶走的原因
she would yell and scream at the trash lady,
她會對著收垃圾的女士怒吼、咆叫
and curse her name.
並咒罵她
To me,
對我來說
it was just all part of a
這就只是
kind of wildness in the world.
這世界裡失控的一小角
The way the plants are always growing
如同植物攀
all over everything
附生長上每件事物
and taking it over.
直到顛覆掌控
Like all the creatures all around,
像生長在大地上的所有物種
just waiting on the edge of the woods
總是帶著黑暗與飢渴的眼神
with their dark and hungry eyes.
躲藏在邊緣伺機行動
There's bugs and things eating each other
昆蟲與其他生物獵殺著彼此
and buzzing all around us.
殘殺的聲響環繞著我們
Even the air is at war with us,
甚至連空氣都參與了這場戰爭
rusting stuff all over
物件不斷的腐敗
and eating it up from the inside.
並從內部蠶食個精光
The papers talked all about wars,
報紙上提到的都是戰爭、
and diseases,
疾病、
and the dinosaurs,
與暴力
and how they got wiped from the earth.
以及它們如何從這個地球上被抹滅
How they were here one day,
又如何存在在這世上
and then -
然後的然後
poof.
砰
We would play by the
我們會在夜晚時
sometimes at night,
到水邊玩耍
and we were always turning up old bottles
總會翻找出些舊瓶子
and stuff that nobody had ever seen before.
和一些從沒看過的東西
Just old junk from some other civilizations,
其實也就只是些從其他文化地方來的老舊垃圾
washed ashore in the mud
夾帶著泥
with all the fiddler crabs.
和招潮蟹沖上岸
My mother's funeral was postponed a while
母親的喪禮順延一陣子
because they were studying her body,
因為他們再對她的身體做測試
and analyzing its decomposition.
分析腐壞的部分
The memorial service was in the winter,
追悼會是在冬季
around the time of year
一年左右的時間
that everyone in town was burning leaves,
鎮上的每個人都在燃燒樹葉
and the whole air
整個空氣就像又濕
smelled like a wet, smoky dog.
又煙霧瀰漫的味道
I think it was the smell that
我想是這些味道給了
gave me the idea,
我這個想法
and then it was like I just knew,
接著它變成了我所熟知的味道
or that I had known for a long time.
或者應該說是我早知道很久的味道了
That she would not be
那她不會出
at the memorial service.
現在追悼會
That she would not be at the house.
不會出現在房子裡
Even when I went to the dump,
即使是去垃圾場
I never expected to see that chair.
我都不再期待看見那張座椅
How had she moved it,
他是如何搬走它的
all by herself?
全靠她一個人？
Why did she take it to the water to burn?
她為什麼要搬去水邊焚燒？
What was it about that chair?
這座椅到底有甚麼好追究的？
It's been a long time
自從母親去世後
since my mother died,
也過了好久
but I still think about
但我依舊不時
the strange black smoke
想起那詭異的黑煙
coming up from that chair,
從座椅上漸漸升起
filled with the mold
夾雜著黴
that had infested it and
那侵擾著母親並深入
burrowed into my mother's brain.
至她的大腦的黴病
At that moment
那一剎那
I felt a kind of peaceful terror.
我感到一種平靜的恐懼感
Was it in my body too, even then?
即使這樣它是否也存在在我體內？
Growing in my lungs,
在肺部裡成長
and making it's way to my eyes?
一路擴散到我的眼睛？
I knew somehow
我知道無論如何
that the troubles in our town
城鎮裡的困擾
would soon be over,
很快就會結束的
and in fact
然而事實上
the mold did leave soon after,
之後黴病確很快地消失了
never to return.
再也沒有出現過
And yet,
然而
part of me did not want this to be true.
一部分的我卻不希望這些是真的
I wanted to breathe in the mold,
我希望在瀰漫著黴的空氣裡呼吸著
just to know it.
了解它
To have it grow inside of me ...
讓他在我體內生長
Over my eyes,
佈滿我的雙眼
and my teeth,
和牙齒
so that I would be in the ground
這樣一來我就會被埋進地底
and become it ...
而成為它
become a kind of mold myself
使自己成為一種黴
and then float through the air
飄散在空氣中
and grow inside of you.
並在你身體裡茁壯
Inside the wet, warm insides of your body,
濕潤又溫暖的體內
until we were all the same thing.
直到我們都成為黴病為止